Virginia Radley Papers
State University of New York at Oswego
Virginia Radley Papers
1973 - 1997
Professional collection of Dr. Virginia Radley, the eighth president of SUNY Oswego. Dr. Radley, the first woman president of a state-operated campus in the SUNY system, led the way to bolstering Oswego’s strong commitment to academic quality. She shepherded the establishment of the college’s Honors Program, Quest day of scholarly and creative activity and other endeavors that continue to provide depth and diversity to the Oswego experience.
2.33 linear feet
Radley, Virginia L.
State University of New York at Oswego Penfield Library 7060 State Route 104 Oswego, New York 13126-3599
1999.007.0001
Collection is open to the public
Dr. Virginia Radley was the eighth president of SUNY Oswego from 1978 to 1988. She came to Oswego in 1974 as provost and executive vice president. Radley became acting president for two months in 1976 and was inaugurated president on October 7, 1978. Virginia Radley was the first woman president in SUNY. During her term as president she increased the enrollment of minorities at SUNY Oswego and supported affirmative action in recruiting and promoting faculty and staff. Academic excellence was stressed, and she revised a general education program and developed the honors program in Liberal Studies. She also worked for women's rights and better academic advising. Sheldon Hall was placed on the register of historic landmarks during her administration. She resigned in 1988 to teach English.
Dr. Radley was Chairman of the English Department at Russell Sage College, Troy, New York in 1966. She received a B.A. from Russell Sage College, an M.A. from the University of Rochester and an M.S. and Ph.D. from Syracuse University.
She taught at Goucher College and lectured at Syracuse University and Nazareth College.
Javits, Jacob K. (Jacob Koppel), 1904-1986; State University College (Oswego, N.Y.); Oswego (N.Y.); Krupsak, Mary Anne; Eggers, Melvin A.; Ferraro, Geraldine; Ludwig, Coy L., 1939-; College presidents
Contains Radley's correspondence starting from 1973 and ending in 1993. Contains newspaper clippings and other published material about Radley from the 1970's to the 1990's. There are copies of her speeches from 1974 to 1975. Contains copies of her published work, information about her inauguration and information about her resignation. Also includes a plaque presented to Dr. Radley.
Chronologically and by type of record.
The Virginia Radley Papers were largely together and arranged prior to the added work done in 1999. In March 1999, the scattered fragments of Radley's Papers which had been filed elsewhere were gathered together and added to the existing arrangement to make one intact collection. New sources of information by or about Virginia Radley were also interfiled with the already processed Radley papers in the possession of Special Collections. Most of these were from Lynn Ekfelt at St. Lawrence University, but one folder apparently was sent by Dr. Radley to Nancy Osborne in 1994. Some clippings from other collections were also rounded up and added. The series of appointment books was received by Special Collections' Coordinator Nancy Osborne from Dr. Natalie Woodall. Addition papers were added in 2006. Papers were gathered from throughout Special Collections, additional newspaper clippings were added and photographs were scanned into this record.
- Correspondence, 1973 - 1974 (Box-folder 01-01)
  Letters from the office of Dr. Virginia L. Radley. Correspondents include: Dr. Robert McFarland, Assistant Dean of Graduate Studies, SUNY Albany. Elizabeth Luce Moore, Board of Trustees, State University of New York. Richard C. Wheeler, Associate Dean for Academic Affairs, SUNY Oswego. C. Peter Magrath, President, SUNY Binghamton. Also includes schedule of activities for Dr. Radley, Provost of Undergraduate Education. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Correspondence, 1976 - 1977 (Box-folder 1-2)
  Papers relating to invitations to Dr. Radley to submit her name for college president at a variety of colleges. Correspondents include: Charles M. Evans, Associate Provost, SUNY Albany. Patti McGill Peterson to Dr. Walter E. Beach, Mount Vernon College, Presidential Search Committee, Washington, D.C. Francis B. Nimick, Jr.,Chairman, Presidential Search Committee, Chatham College, Pittsburgh, PA. David L. Powers, Presidential Search Committee, Colby-Sawyer College, New London, New Hampshire. James F. Kelly, Acting Chancellor, SUNY, Albany, NY. Donna Shavlik, Associate Director, American Council on Education, Washington, D.C. Jennie Farley, Assistant Professor, New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations, Cornell University, Ithaca, NY. Mary Anne Krupsak, Lieutenant Governor, State of New York, Albany. Mrs. Maurice T. (Beth) Moore, SUNY, Albany, NY. Sally C. Nevius, Board of Trustees, Mount Vernon College, Washington, D.C. Henry Strong, Washington, D.C. Bruce Dearing, Professor, Upstate Medical Center, Syracuse, NY. Leyden E. Brown, Presidential Search Committee, SUNY Oswego. Dorothy Rogers, Professor, SUNY Oswego. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Correspondence- People off campus, 1978 (Box-folder 1-3)
  Letters of congratulations and support. Correspondents include: Reatha Clark King, President, Metropolitan State University, Saint Paul, MN. Coy L. Ludwig, Tyler Art Gallery Director, SUNY Oswego. Lewis C. Popham, 3rd., Dean, Continuing Education & Summer Sessions, SUNY Oswego. John R. Zagame, Assemblyman, Albany, NY. Memorandum from Clifton R. Wharton, Jr., to the Board of Trustees, State University of New, Albany, NY. Re: Appointment of Virginia L. Radley as President, College at Oswego. Includes Dr. Radley's vitae. Melvin A. Eggers, Chancellor, Syracuse University. James W. Hall, Empire State College, Saratoga Springs, NY. Robert McLaughlin, President, Herkimer County Community College, Herkimer, NY. Carol A. Hawkes, Vice President for Educational Affairs and Dean of the College, Hartwick College, Oneonta, NY. Doris L. Eder, Dean of Faculty, Schenectady County Community College, Schenectady, NY. Barbara Meinert, State Education Department, Albany, NY. Alvin P. Lierheimer, Associate Commissioner for Higher Education, State Education Department, Albany, NY. Dr. Cash Kowalski, Vice President for Academic Affairs, SUNY, Agricultural and Technical College, Morrisville, NY. William F. Kahl, President, Russell Sage College, Troy, NY. James J. Parry, Labor Relations Coordinator, State University System of Florida. Frank P. Piskor, President, St. Lawrence University, Canton, NY. Nenah E. Fry, Dean, Wells College, Aurora, NY. Carol George, Hobert & William Smith Colleges, Geneva, NY. Richard C. Jones, President, SUNY Cortland. Harriet F. Bradley, Vice Rector, George Mason University, Fairfax, VA. John R. Haines, Director, State Education Department, Albany, NY. Helen B. Power, Regent Emerita, Univerity of the State of New York, State Education Dept. Sister Marie Augustine, Nazareth College. Richard C. Schmidt, M.D., President, Upstate Medical Center, Syracuse, NY. Stuart Steiner, President, Genesee Community College, Batavia, NY. Barbara R. Frey, Vice President for Academic Affairs, SUNY Buffalo. Charles B. Neff, Provost for Academic Programs, State University of N.Y., Albany. William R. Porter, Vice President for Academic Affairs, SUNY Maritime College, Fort Schuyler, Bronx, NY. Dallas K. Beal, President, SUNY Fredonia. George Keller, Assistant to the Chancellor, Editor, Search, a Journal of Scholarly Research, Albany, NY. Jane Graham, Assistant to the Executive Vice Chancellor, SUNY, Albany, NY. Francis T. Farenthold, President, Wells College, Aurora, NY. Dr. Edward N. Garno, Supervisor of Communications and Personnel, Hudson City School District, Hudson, NY. W. Robert Holmes, Associate Director, Schenectady County Community College. Priscilla J. Angelo, Associate Director of Student Services, St. Lawrence University, Canton, NY. Carol Bollinger, Director, Board of Cooperative Educational Services, Johnstown, NY. John S. Toll, President, SUNY StonyBrook. Oscar Smukler, Acting President, Erie Community College, Buffalo, NY. Richard C. Debus, Assistant Vice President for Administration, Empire State College. Marcia B. Dugan, Director of Public Relations, Keuka College, Keuka Park, NY. Charles M. Evans, Dean, College of Arts & Sciences, University of Evansville, IN. Arthur J. Dudley, Chief, SUNY State Education Department, Albany, NY. Frederick M. Binder, President, Juniata College, Huntingdon, PA. J. W. Peltason, American Council on Eduacation, Washington, D.C. Walter E. Beach, Assistant Director, APSA, Washington, D.C. Robert D. Larsson, President, Schenectady County Community College. Robert A. Kidera, President, Nazareth College of Rochester, NY. Peter D. Pelham, Vice President, Institute of International Education, Washington, D.C. T. Edward Hollander, Chancellor, State of New Jersey Department of Higher Education. Mauro S. Zulli, Acting President, State University, Agricultural and Technical College, Farmington, NY. Elizabeth A. Brinkman, Associate Professor, Wittenberg University, Springfield, OH. Lewis C. Popham, 3rd, President-Elect, Association for Continuing Higher Education. Jacquelyn Anderson Mattfeld, President, Barnard College, Columbia University, NY. Virginia Kemp, Assistant Vice President for Academic Affairs, SUNY Geneseo. Lawrence K. Pettit, Commissioner of Higher Education, The Montana University System, Helena, MT. David L. Powers, Assistant to the President for Development, Colby-Sawyer College, New London, NH. Eileen M. Kolynich, Director, Career Planning & Placement, Fordham University. D. Kenneth Baker, President, Harvey Mudd College, Claremont, CA. William S. Fuller, Executive Director, Nebraska Coordinating Commission for Postsecondary Education, Lincoln, NE. Harold Delaney, Associate Executive Director, American Association of State Colleges and Universities, Washington, D.C. Dr. Mary Ann Biller, Dean, Empire State College, Lower Hudson Regional Learning Center at White Plains, NY. Carl J. Schneider, Dean of Graduate Studies, Monclair State University, Upper Monclair, NJ. Francis N. Hamblin, President, Lock Haven State College, Lock Haven, PA.. Carey W. Brush, Vice President for Academic Affairs, SUNY Oneonta. Robert MacVittie, President, SUNY Geneseo. Corinne C. Turner, Chairman of the Board of Trustees, Colby-Sawyer College, New London, NH. Martha E. Church, President, Hood College, Frederick, MD. Reatha Clark King, President, Metropolitan State University, Saint Paul, MN. Barbara Wetheimer, Director, Institute for Education & Research on Women and Work, Cornell University. Barbara W. Newell, President, Wellesley College. William W. Jellema, President, Wartburg College, Waverly, Iowa. Alberta Arthurs, President, Chatham College, Pittsburgh, PA. Harriet D. Hudson, Provost and Dean, St. Mary's College of Maryland. Virginia L. Lester, President, Mary Baldwin College, Staunton, VA. Edwin T. Carine, Jr., Director, Middle State Regional Office, The College Board, Bethlehem, PA. John J. Connolly, President, Dutchess Community College, SUNY Poughkeepsie. Leonard R. Kershaw, Assistant Director, State of New York Executive Department Office of Employee Relations, Albany, NY. Richard D. Robbins, Associate Dean, The Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD. Robert Kirkwood, Executive Director, Commission on Higher Education, Philadelphia, PA. Stanley J. Drazek, Chancellor, University of Maryland, University College, College Park, MD. Brunetta R. Wolfman, Academic Dean, Wheelock College, Boston, MA. Joseph N. Hankin, President, Westchester Community College, Valhalla, NY. Peter J. Cayan, President, North Country Community College, Saranac, NY. Stephen L. Weber, Vice President for Academic Affairs, St. Cloud State University, St. Cloud, Minnesota. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Correspondence- People on Campus, 1978 (Box-folder 1-4)
  Letters, memorandum and cards of congratulations and support. Correspondents include: Fred Bartle, UUP Executive Committee. Women's Health and Physical Education Department. John Kares Smith, Associate Professor, Communication Studies. Lois Jackim. David M. H. Richmond. John C. Fisher, Chairman, Faculty Assembly. Financial Aids Office. Lois Jean Coleman. George H. Koenig. Ellen Hemink. Helen and Dave Glick. Dick Pfund, Director, Learning Resources Center. Mark H. Salter, Editor, "On The Case". Nevart Boghasian, Elementary Education. Jon Bartow. Robert H. Peterson. George Scheck. Mandy Bratton, student. Joan Huff. Herb Garber. Constance Finlay, Director, Waterbury Hall. Marcia C. Moore. Sandy Sternlicht. Ted DiPasquale. Ann Robson, Alumni Association. Stephen Torok. Bob Sykes. Dr. Stephen Meisel, Chairman, Reading Education Department. Coy L. Ludwig. T. C. Eckersley, Associate Professor and Chairman, Department of Art. Mary H. Glann. Elizabeth hull, Political Science Department. Johnson G. Cooper, Professor Emeritus. Elearnor Filburn. Dr. Arthur Sabatini, Acting Director of International Education. Albert C. Leighton. Lewis B. O'Donnell. Martin J. Lindenmayer, President, Student Association. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Correspondence- Local People, 1978 (1-5)
  Letters of congratulations and support. Correspondents include: Warren P. Zoni, Zoni Bros. Furniture and Appliance. Peter L. Dziedzic, Assistant Secretary, Columbia Banking Saving and Loan Association. Cathy Richardson, Syracuse, NY. Burton Ramer, District Supervisor, Oswego County Board of Cooperative Educational Services, Mexico, NY. David W. Pelland, Menter, Rudin & Trivelpiece, Syracuse, NY. Gerald J. Ware, Assistant Banking Officer & Manager, Marine Midland Bank, Oswego, NY. Bruce H. Whitney, Vice President, Marine Midland Bank, Oswego, NY. William J. Bower, Superintendent of Schools, Board of Education, Fulton, NY. Charles W. Gilbert. H. Douglas Barclay, Senator, State of New York. Foster S. Brown, Pompano Beach, FL. Edward P. Caraccioli, Principal, Fitzhugh Park School, Oswego. Jacob K. Javits, New York State Senator. Emmett J. Schnepp, Justice, Supreme Court, Hall of Justice, Rochester, NY. Mr. and Mrs. Lester Gosier ('37), Bay Shore, NY. Andrew D. Virgilio, Assemblyman 133rd District, New York State. Robert W. Brutsch, Field Director, Northwestern Mutual Life Insurance Co., Milwaukee. Joan Fitzgibbons. Margaret L. Lovell. Madge Tompkins. Leila C. McBride, Hamburg, NY. Charles F. Wells. Francine Wattman Frank, Albany, NY. Helen H. Burnside, Dean, School of Nursing, University of Hawaii at Manoa. Donald W. Watson, (class of 1977), Fitzgibbons-Sindoni, Inc., Mexico, NY. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Correspondence- Friends, 1978 (Box-folder 1-6)
  Cards and notes of congratulations and support. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Correspondence- Friends, 1978 (Box-folder 1-7)
  Letters of congratulations and support. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Certificates of Congratulation, 1978 (Box-folder 1-8)
  Two Certificates of Congratulations on the Appointment of Dr. Virginia L. Radley's appointment as President. One certificate is from SUNY Cortland. The second certificate is from Dutchess Community College. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Memoranda, 1976 - 1988 (Box-folder 1-12)
  Memoranda from the office of Dr. Virginia L. Radley. Recipients and subjects include: Dr. Donald Mathieu Dr. William Drake, English Department Chairperson. The College Community Chancellor's Award for Excellence in Administrative Services List of eligible candidates. The Faculty Reviewing mission statements. The Faculty and Staff Search committee for the Dean of Arts and Sciences. The Faculty and Staff Presentation by David C. Crockett. The College Community Invitation for applications for the position of Acting Assistant to the President for Community Relations. The College Community (Draft) Evaluate the performance of acting administrators now in positions for one year. Faculty and Staff Alumni Phonathon. The Faculty State car utilization. Campus Community Hiring freeze and fiscal restraints. The College Community Position freeze. The College Community State budget. Members of the College Council Proposal to cut faculty and staff positions. The College Community College Policy on Sexual Harassment. Faculty + Staff Budget. All Faculty, Resident Assistants and Professional Staff National Collegiate Alcohol Awareness Week reception. Members of the College Community Executive Vice-President/Provost Appointment. (Formerly 1/9/157)
- College Policies/Reports, 1986 (Box-folder 1-13)
  Information dealing with Forsight, women in SUNY college at Oswego and college policy on sexual harassment. President's 1986 report to SUNY administration on budget and other campus issues. (Formerly 1/9/140)
- Speeches, 1973 - 1975 (Box-folder 1-14)
  Speeches of Dr. Virginia L. Radley including the following: Involvement of Women in the Governance Process: Decision Making. December 1973. 17 typed pages. Includes 11-page draft with editing notes. Exceeding One's Grasp: A view of excellence. SUNY Brockport Honors Convocation speech. April 3, 1974. Includes 9-page typed draft with editing notes, Honors Convocation program, and thank you letter from John C. Crandall, Vice President for Instruction and Curriculum, State University College at Brockport. 2 copies of speech. The Man Faces of Eve: Some SUNY Firsts. Six typed pages. n.d. Speech given to the open meeting of the Academic Policies Council on September 11, 1975. Six typed pages with editing notes. "Discipline Versus the 'Viewless Wings of Poesy' " by Virginia L. Radley. Reprint from Liberal Education, Vol. XLIX, No. 4, December 1963. Six pages. Untitled speech on post-secondary education. n.d. 12 typed pages. Untitled speech on the historical context within which women have moved, stood still, or fled in and from the groves of academe. n.d. 4 typed pages. Welcome speech at the opening ceremonies of the 1975 New York State Association of Intercollegiate Athletics for Women's Volleyball Tournament. 1-page typed speech. Trends in Adminstration of Higher Education in the 70's. Thirteen page draft with editing notes. 26-page speech with editing notes. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Speeches, 1976 - 1977 (Box-folder 1-15)
  Speeches of Dr. Virginia L. Radley including the following: "Smite the Sounding Furrows". Address given by Dr. Virginia L. Radley, Executive Vice President/Provost, State University College at Oswego, at a conference entitled, "Road to Survival: Financial Management in a Changing Environment," sponsored by the State Education Department, February 25, 1976. Thirteen typed pages with bibliography. Also includes six pages of handwritten notes. Edited. Remarks on Expectations for the Administrative Team. June 1977. Includes memorandum, typed with editing notes, and handwritten notes. 10 pages. Two copies of typed memorandum. Invitation from Delat Kappa Gamma, Alpha Iota Chapter, to speak at meeting. June 1977. Speech to Resident Assistants. August 1977. Seven handwritten pages. Welcome new students. Third Curriculum. August 30, 1977. Nine handwritten pages. Speech to freshmen. August 30, 1977. Eight pages of handwritten notes. Founder's Day Address. Russell Sage College. October 6, 1977. Eight pages. 3 copies. Informal Evening with Waterbury and Scales Hall at Waterbury. October 11, 1977. 6 handwritten pages. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Speeches, January, 1978 - April, 1978 (Box-folder 1-16)
  Speeches of Dr. Virginia L. Radley including the following: State of the college. March 1978. Seven handwritten pages. View from a new president. March 1978. Six handwritten pages. Issues and/or concerns of VLR at Oswego. Two handwritten pages. Talk to Vice Presidents. January 9, 1978. Six handwritten pages. Welcome to new students. January 15, 1978. Four handwritten pages. Talk to Vice Presidents. February 6, 1978. Two handwritten pages. State of the college. February 1978. Five typed pages. Rotary Club. April 25, 1978. Seven typed pages, 1 page of handwritten notes. Edited. Industrial Arts speech. April 29, 1978. 14 pages, includes edited version, handwritten notes and copy. RA's and assistants. April 1978. Five handwritten pages with newspaper clipping. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Speeches, May, 1978 - December, 1978 (Box-folder 1-17)
  Speeches of Dr. Virginia L. Radley including the following: ROTC speech. May 5, 1978. Six pages. Typed. Remarks to YWCA. May 9, 1978. Eight pages with editing notes. Typed. Speech to Faculty. May 10, 1978. Five handwritten pages, one typed. Alice Foley Lecture: Nazareth College of Rochester. July 19, 1978. Eight pages. Address to Freshman. August 1978. Three typed pages. Faculty meeting. August 31, 1978. Six typed pages with editing notes. I.A. Speech. Fall 1978. Seven handwritten pages. New York State Education Department Upper Mohawk/Hudson Conference. September 26, 1978. Nine typed pages with editing notes. "The Infinite Kingdom of Mind". Inaugural address. October 7, 1978. Seven typed pages. Notes for speech to the American Council on Education Forum on Credentials. October 27, 1978. Five typed pages with editing notes. Remarks for the Modern Language Association. Special Session: The Teaching of Literature and Values. December 1978. Seven typed pages with editing notes. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Speeches, January, 1979 - April, 1979 (Box-folder 1-18)
  Speeches of Dr. Virginia L. Radley including the following: State of the College. January 1979. Six pages. Typed and handwritten, edited. President's List. February 4, 1979. Six handwritten pages. State of College - One Year After. Spring 1979. Three handwritten pages. "Circe and the Colossus: Seductive actors on the Horizon". March 1979. 3 copies. NAWDHC. April 7, 1979. Three typed pages, edited. Remarks in Wisconsin in a plenary session, "Personal Advancement Issues". April 1979. 5 typed pages, edited. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Speeches, May, 1979 - December, 1979 (Box-folder 1-19)
  Speeches of Dr. Virginia L. Radley including the following: Mansions of Mind. Maria Regina College. May 1979. Commencement Address. 5 typed pages, editing notes. Convocation. School of Education. Syracuse University. May 11, 1979. 3 typed pages. 3 copies. Marion High School Commencement. June 22, 1979. Three typed pages. 3 copies. Also includes correspondence between Dr. Radley and Marion High School representatives. Commencement progam. To New Faculty and Staff. September 4, 1979. Four handwritten pages. Remarks for the Opening Faculty Meeting. September 6, 1979. Five pages, editing notes. SUNY Retention newsletter. October 1979. Ten pages. To Faculty and Students, re: budget. December 1979. Eleven handwritten pages. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Speeches, January, 1980 - May, 1980 (Box-folder 1-20)
  Speeches of Dr. Virginia L. Radley including the following: Remarks to the General Faculty. March 13, 1980. Nine typed and handwritten pages, edited. Also includes 13-page edited version. Speech for AWPENY's conference. March 15, 1980. Thirteen typed pages, edited. Also includes Anne Mackey Lecture program, Kiamesha Lake, New York. Remarks to Chatham Hall. April 18, 1980. Handwritten notes, 5 pages. Research talk. April 23, 1980. Handwritten notes, 6 pages. "Wingspread Conference Speech. The 1980's: Women and Higher Education". Seven typed pages, edited. General Faculty meeting. April 30, 1980. Seven pages, edited. "Upward Mobility for Women". May 6, 1980. 8 pages, edited. Remarks to be made to the Conference of Presidents. May 11, 1980. Five typed pages, edited. Retirement dinner. May 19, 1980. Two pages, handwritten, edited. (Formerly 1/9/194)
- Speeches, June, 1980 - December, 1980 (Box-folder 1-21)